Hopkins, Vivian C.; Papers ua902.003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Vivian C. Hopkins Papers
1861-1984
1930-1980
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua902.003
14.59 cubic ft.
This collection consists of the papers of Dr. Vivian Constance Hopkins. These papers document Dr. Hopkins's career in academia, her personal correspondence, familial materials, and the records of the Albany Gravel Company.
Collection X
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily includes correspondence, diaries, and Vivian Hopkins' research materials and secondary sources. Correspondence of note includes the Naoshi Koriyama letters, the Virginia French letters, and the Civil War letters of William Brown and Emma Frazey, Hopkins' maternal grandparents. In addition to Hopkins' personal diaries, the collection includes the original Civil War Diary of William Brown from 1861-1864, as well as Hopkins' transcriptions. Hopkins' research materials include the following topics: the portrayal of Satan in literature, Robert Frost, Ralph Waldo Emerson, DeWitt Clinton, Delia Bacon, Francis Bacon, Margaret Fuller, and Francis Adrian Van Der Kamp.
Additionally, the collection includes typescripts, drafts, and final publications of serial articles, short stories and monographs written by Hopkins which directly relate to her research materials. Monographs include Prodigal Puritan: a Life of Delia Bacon and Spires of Form: A Study of Emerson's Aesthetic Theory. The collection has correspondence with publishers and materials that relate not only to the publication of these monographs, but other works and serials, regardless of if she was successful in publishing them.
The Hopkins Papers also include the records of the Albany Gravel Company, also known as Albany Gravel Co., up to the company's liquidation in 1980. Hopkins' father, John B. Hopkins, and her brother, Richard W. Hopkins, both served as presidents of the company, and Vivian Hopkins later served on the Board of Directors.
Biographical Sketch
Vivian Constance Hopkins was born in Troy in 1909. She received a high school degree from Lansingburgh High School, a B.A. in English from Wellesley College, an M.A. in playwriting from the University of Michigan, an M.A. in English from Radcliffe College, and finally her Ph.D. in English from the University of Michigan in 1943. During her time at the University of Michigan, Hopkins would become friends, and potentially, a romantic partner, with Virginia Adeline French, with letters in the collection from 1941 to 1945 (of those with dates). In 1941, Hopkins joined the faculty of the New York State College for Teachers (today known as the University at Albany) as an English professor. During her time at the New York State College for Teachers, she received a Guggenheim Fellowship in 1956 for her study of Francis Bacon and his influence on American thought in the early 19th century. In addition to her work on Francis Bacon, Hopkins published on other literary figures including Nathanial Hawthorne, Delia Bacon, Margaret Fuller, Robert Frost, and Ralph Waldo Emerson. She also conducted research on the sixth governor of New York State, DeWitt Clinton. During her time at the College, Dr. Hopkins became the mentor and later, friend, of her student Naoshi Koriyama, who studied English Literature and graduated in 1954. Koriyama became a poet and professor in Japan. Dr. Hopkins would continue in her role as a Professor of English when the College became the State University of New York at Albany in 1962, retiring in 1973. She died in 1989. Prior to her death, Dr. Hopkins assisted with the liquidation of the Albany Gravel Company, which was created by her father, John B. Hopkins. During her retirement, she worked to establish The Vivian C. Hopkins Scholarship Award at the University at Albany, SUNY for outstanding scholastic ability and character in the Department of English. For a biographical sketch and remembrance from a student and later colleague of Hopkins, Arthur N. Collins, see the file on Hopkins in the Faculty Reference Collection: <//archives.albany.edu/description/catalog/ua950-003aspace_ae07e0e268184c525bdba0fbefd93039.</>
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: Personal and Family Papers; General Research, Writings, and Publication Materials; and the Albany Gravel Company Records. Within each series, the folders are arranged alphabetically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
All items in this collection were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives in 1986 by Vivian C. Hopkins.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
UAlbany Faculty & Alumni Papers; Hopkins, Vivian C. (Vivian Constance), 1909-1989; Correspondence.; English--Education; Literature; English literature--Study and teaching (Higher); Education, Higher--New York (State)
- Personal and Family Papers, 1861-1984; 1930-1970; 4 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Folders in this series are arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series is made up Hopkins' correspondence, genealogy materials, photographs, newspaper clippings, some diaries, as well as correspondence belonging to other members of her family that mention her, all of which ranging the entirety of her life. Hopkins is often addressed as "Vivian," "Beech," "Bizzy," and "Constance." The correspondence includes letters and poems from Virginia A. (Adeline) French. These letters, sometimes signed letters as "G.A." or "Ginny Addy," are strongly suggestive a romantic relationship between the women from 1942 to 1945 (of those that have dates on them). While Hopkins occasionally kept a duplicate of her correspondence with individuals and publishers, she did not create any duplicates of her letters to Virginia French. It is unknown what happened to French and the true scope and length of the relationship between two women. Additionally, there are the letters, newsclippings and photographs between Hopkins and her former student, the Japanese poet and professor Naoshi Koriyama. These materials range from 1954 to 1979 and are a mix of correspondence relating to literature and English and Japanese academia to details and updates of Koriyama's life. Hopkins also was a friend of the American Poet, Robert Frost, and the series includes Christmas poetry booklets with personal notes to Hopkins. Finally, this series also includes the diary of her grandfather during his time in the Civil War.
  - "824 Second Avenue [Property Management]", 1941-1967; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Abbie Potts M.S.", 1958-1966; Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Academic Records Official", 1930-1931; 1938-1941; 1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ambrose Bierce Event Flyer, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - American Literature Contract Numbers 1 and 2 Assignment, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Am[erican] Studies 1967 Hamilton College", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Aunt May's Geneaology Book, Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Aunt May's Geneaology Book, Loose Material, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Aunt May's [Geneaology] Records", 1978; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bennet Junior College Presidency Candidate Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "B.F.H. Frazey Spanish Affair", 1909 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "B.F.H. Frazey Spanish Affair", 1910; Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Certificate H[igh] School Teaching", 1930-1931 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Civil War Diary [of W.H. Brown]", 1861-1864 (Oversize 1)
  - "Civil War Diary [of W.H. Brown]," Correspondence, 1966-1967; 1969; 1974; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Civil War Diary [of W.H. Brown]," Transcription, Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings from the New York State College for Teachers Alumni Quarterly, Volume 40, Number 3, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "[Cornell] Alpha Chi Rho [Gifts]", 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Cornell Scholarship", 1970; 1976-1979; Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), 1929 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), 1941 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, c. 1940S (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence (1 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence (2 of 2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Dedication of Memorial Elevator for Josephine Brown Hopkins and Richard William Hopkins at United Methodist Church of Lansingburgh, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Diary: "Daily Reminder" Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, 1921 (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: "Five Year Diary" [Green] Potentially Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: "Five Year Diary" [Blue] Potentially Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: "A Line a Day" Loose Materials, 1927-1929; Undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Diary: "A Line a Day" Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, 1927-1929 (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: "Memorandum Book" Potentially Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: Mentioning Vivian C. Hopkins, 1955 (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: Mentioning Vivian C. Hopkins, 1960 (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: Mentioning Vivian C. Hopkins, 1961 (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: Mentioning Vivian C. Hopkins Loose Materials, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Diary: "Mile Stones: A Five Year Diary" Potentially Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, 1932 (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: Potentially Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Diary: "The Standard Diary" Loose Materials, 1926; Undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Diary: "The Standard Diary" Owned by Vivian C. Hopkins, 1926 (Oversize 1)
  - "Dick Shorrett", 1977; Undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Donations to Archives, Historical Societies, Libraries, and Trust Funds, 1965-1967; 1973; 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "[Dr. Shields] McIlwaine", 1972 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - "[Edith O.] Wallace Tributes", 1970; 1972; Undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Emerson and Bacon Pamphlet Correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Encyclopedia of American Biography, Richard Hopkins, 1961; Undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - English 1B Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - English 2 Notebook, Undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - English 2B and 2C Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - English 3B and 3C Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - English 3 Volleyball Championship Card for Vivian C. Hopkins, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - "English 100a Course Assignments", Undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - "English 110 Term Paper Directions", Undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - English Composition 101R, 203B, and 207B Writings by Vivian C. Hopkins, 1926-1928; 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - English Literature 178 Materials, Undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Estate of Richard Hopkins Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - The Fairytale-Tours of Denmark Materials and Correspondence, 1970; Undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - "Final Examination English 205", Undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Financial Ledger with Payments and Short Story, 1896-1898; Undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Frazey Family Geneaology, Undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - "Freihofer Bread Wagon [Photographic Film]", Undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - "Fulbright", 1964-1966; Undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - "Harvard University May 8, 1939 Preliminary Examination for Candidates for the PhD in English Philology" (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Hopkins Family Geneaology Book, Undated (Oversize 1)
  - Hopkins Family Geneaology Materials, 1964; 1974; Undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - "ISU [Iowa State University] Alumni and Illinois State Historical Library", 1969; 1975 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Josephine Brown Hopkins' Diary, 1972; Undated (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Lansingburgh High School Academic Diploma, 1926 (Map-tube 1)
  - Lansingburgh High School College Entrance Diploma, 1926 (Map-tube 1)
  - "LHS [Lansingburgh] High School] Alumni 50th [Reunion for the Class of 1926]", 1976; Undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - "LHS [Lansingburgh High School] Commencement", 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - "Letters from N. Koriyama to V. Hopkins, 1954-1959", 1951; Undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - "Letters from N. Koriyama to V. Hopkins, 1960-1969", 1960-1965; 1967-1969; Undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - "Letters from N. Koriyama to V. Hopkins, 1970-1975" (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - "Letters from N. Koriyama to V. Hopkins, 1976" (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - "Letters from N. Koriyama to V. Hopkins, 1977" (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Letters from Naoshi Koriyama to Vivian C. Hopkins, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - "Letters of William H. Brown and Emma Jane Frazey Edited by Vivian C. Hopkins", 1968; Undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - "Letters of William H. Brown and Emma Jane Frazey From September 14, 1862 - May 1, 1867", Undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Letters of William Brown and Emma Frazey, Originals, 1862; 1864-1867; Undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Letters of William Brown and Emma Frazey, Transcribed, Undated (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - "Letters to N. Koriyama from V. Hopkins, 1954-1976", 1945; 1954-1965; 1967-1976; Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - "Lillian Jones and Albert Jones [v. Richard Hopkins, John B. Hopkins, and Vivian C. Hopkins]", 1954; Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Map Showing Lands of Vivian Hopkins", Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - "Margaret Fuller: Pioneer Women's Liberationist [Article and Correspondence]", 1972-1973; Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Master of Arts Degree from University of Michigan, 1931 (Map-tube 1)
  - Materials Donated by Vivian C. Hopkins, 1961; 1963; 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Midyear Examination - English 101 ABCD", Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Mother's [Josephine Brown Hopkins'] Account of her Wedding", Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - New York Public Library Bulletin Correspondence, 1864; 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - New York State College for Teachers Job, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "N[ew] Y[ork] S[tate] C[ollege for] T[eachers] Job", 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - New York State Historical Association and Henry Allen Moe's Death, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "N[ew] Y[ork] S[tate] C[ollege for] T[eachers] Retirement", 1971 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Obit[uarie]s on Father", 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Picture: Newton and Fall of Apple", 1956 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Photo-Engraved Metal Panel of Naoshi Koriyama and Wife Portrait, Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Photographs of Naoshi Koriyama, Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Vivian C. Hopkins, 1932; Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Poetry and Book Reviews of Naoshi Koriyama", 1954-1960; 1972; 1974; 1976-1980; Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Poetry and Book Reviews of Naoshi Koriyama" Oversized Material, 1954-1960; 1972; 1974; 1976-1980; Undated (Oversize 4)
  - "Potter Family and Irwin Smith [Correspondence]", 1976 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Renss[elaer] Co[unty Department of] Aging", 1978; Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Retirement from University [Photographs]", 1971 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Revision Real Prop[erty] Tax", 1950; 1953-1954; 1960; Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "R[ichard] W. H[opkins] Re. Patent", 1945-1949; Undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Robert Frost Christmas Cards and Poems to Vivian C. Hopkins, 1935; 1944; 1953-1956 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Sabattical Leave and Promotion", 1954; 1958; 1964 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Schedule for American Literature, Second Semester, 1962" (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Schedule for English 121 Second Semester, 1967" (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - State University of New York at Albany Correspondence Regarding Wages, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "Student Themes", 1935; 1937; Undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Subject of History Principles and Applications, Undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - "Syracuse University Offer", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Union College Mohawk Drama Festival Certificate, 1935 (Map-tube 1)
  - "University of Michigan Sport Sessions 1932, Course Outline for Field Hockey" (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - University of Michigan, University Bureau of Appointments and Occupational Information Report on Vivian C. Hopkins", 1930-1941 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "[Virginia French and] the Hopwood Room Letter", 1942 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Virginia French Letters (1 of 2), 1941-1945; Undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Virginia French Letters (2 of 2), 1941-1945; Undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - "Virginia French Poetry", 1941-1942; 1948; Undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Vivian C. Hopkins Curriculum Vitae, 1958; 1973-1974; Undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Vivian C. Hopkins English Composition 101R, 1927-1930 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Vivian C. Hopkins English Composition 304 Short Story, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Vivian C. Hopkins, Guggenheim Memorial Fellow, 1955-1958; 1960; 1963; 1975-1976; Undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Vivian C. Hopkins Publication List Draft, Undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "V[ivian] C. H[opkins] Publicity", 1958; Undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Vivian C. Hopkins Russian Certificate from Albany Evening High School, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Vivian C. Hopkins Scholarship, 1971; 1978-1979; 1982; Undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - "Vivian Memoirs", 1927; 1930; Undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - "Wellesley Alumnae Magazine", 1961 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - "Wellesley College Gift of US Steel", 1976-1978; Undated (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - "Wellesley Commencement [Newspaper Clippings]", 1930; Undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - "W.H. Brown Diary and Letters", 1966-1967; Undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - "Whitman Evening [Materials and Notes]", 1955-1956; 1960-1961; Undated (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - "Whitman Evening [Materials and Notes]" Oversized Material, 1955-1956; 1960-1961; Undated (Oversize 4)
  - "Zoning Ordinance: Hopkins - Against - City of Troy", 1960; Undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
- General Research, Writings, and Publication Materials, 1927-1979; 9.5 cubic ft.
  This series is primarily made up of Hopkins' research materials and notes, both typed and handwritten, for scholarly publications as articles, monographs and books. However, it also includes newspaper clippings about her publications, secondary sources that were used in her research process, typescripts, author's galleys, drafts and publication copies of serial articles, fictional short stories and plays, and monographs. Included in this are folders of unidentified research notes and fictional works. Furthermore, it contains correspondence concerning research questions, and correspondence for manuscript proposals, regardless of success or failure to publish them.
  The series focuses on several literary and historical figures, family members, and topics of particular interest to Hopkins. These include DeWitt Clinton, Delia Bacon, Francis Bacon, Herman Melville, Francis Adrian Van Der Kemp, Ralph Waldo Emerson, and the portrayal of Satan in English literature. Included are materials related to her works Prodigal Puritan: A Life of Delia Bacon (1940), Spires of Form: A Study of Emerson's Aesthetic Theory (1951), as well as a number of articles for various serial publications.
  - "AAUW Fellowship", 1945; 1947-1949; 1951; Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Academic Murder Plot", Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Adams [Family Notes]", 1947; 1952; 1954-1955; Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Adams [Family Notes]" Oversized Material, 1947; 1952; 1954-1955; Undated (Oversize 2)
  - "Adams, V.O.K. Letters", 1961; Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Additions to Notes [on Delia Bacon]", 1958-1959; Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alice Bacon Drafts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Allen Hist. Am. Ornithology", Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "America vs. England Allston", Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Literature Bibliography, Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Revolution and Founders Notes, 1953-1967; Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "An Answer to Mr. Samuel Willard", Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Andre Maugars [on Francis Bacon]", Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Arthur Miller Paper with Drafts and Notes (1 of 2), 1952-1953; Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Arthur Miller Paper with Drafts and Notes (2 of 2), 1952-1953; Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Arthur Miller Research Materials, Notes, and Correspondence, 1953-1954; 1957; Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Arthur Miller Research Materials, Notes, and Correspondence Oversized Materials, 1953-1954; 1957; Undated (Oversize 4)
  - "Asa Fitch Diary [Notes]", Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "Atlantic Review William H. Dixon P[ersonal] H[istory of] Lord Bacon", Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Augustine and Aquinas", Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Author's Duplicate of "Spires of Form" with Proofreader Annotations (1 of 2), 1951; Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Author's Duplicate of "Spires of Form" with Proofreader Annotations (2 of 2), 1951; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Author's Galley Proof of "The Governor and the Western Recluse: DeWitt Clinton and Francis Adrian van der Kemp" with Annotations, ca. 1962 (Oversize 4)
  - Author's Galley Proof of "Prodigal Puritan: A Life of Delia Bacon" by Vivian C. Hopkins with Annotations, ca. 1959 (Oversize 4)
  - Author's Galley Proof of "Spires of Form: A Study of Emerson's Aesthetic Theory" by Vivian C. Hopkins with Annotations, ca. 1951 (Oversize 4)
  - Authors and the Depiction of Satan, Undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Bacon and Humanities", Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bacon and Law Notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Bacon Chap[ter] One", Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "Bacon Family [Correspondence]", 1954-1955; 1957-1958; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)